Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin 1730-1776 Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin
1730-1776
Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
1075 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1730 July 14; D.S. 1p.; Meredith, Hugh
    Scope and Contents note
    Dissolution of partnership. All printing material in the office and debts owing to the partners to be the property of Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1735 July 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Morgan, Joseph. Maidenhead
    Concerning the printing of a new edition of "The Temporal Interest of North America." 1 Writes out two paragraphs to be added to the manuscript. Amount of money he has paid him.
    General note
    1 See Hildeburn's Issues of the Penna. Press, No. 496.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1740 November 5; D.S. 1p.; Franklin, James. Philadelphia
    Indenture as apprentice to Benjamin Franklin, printer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1740; L. 3p.; "Constant Reader", AB
    Requests him to insert the accompanying note in his next paper. The note is a letter to a friend, giving some distinguishing characteristics of a certain species of Gospel-preachers, who would have brought more credit to themselves and good to their fellow-men if they had continued in a secular employment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1741 September 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Tennent, Gilbert
    Acknowledging his kindness in sending him certain dissenting remarks on his Sermon on Justifications, likewise in sending the "Querists," 1 lately printed by Franklin; intends to write an answer to the former which will deal with the principal matters in the "Querists." Had the pleasure of discoursing with Franklin's brother in his pass through his place. Trusts that notwithstanding Mr. Franklin's gifts of Nature, he may be kept humble and be enabled to improve his uncommon genius for God's glory, his own and others' benefits.
    1 See Hildeburn's Issues of the Penna. Press, No. 647.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1742 September 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Spicer, Jacob. Cape May
    Asking him to insert the enclosed advertisement; will pay also for his subscription to Mr. Franklin's Gazette.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1746, March 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Dames, William
    Asking that all his letters may be forwarded to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 June 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Books sent by Elias Bland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 June 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Whitefield, Rev. George
    Thanks him for the preamble to the subscription which has for its purpose the raising of funds for the support of the orphan house in which he is personally interested. [Mutilated.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 July 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Turner, James. Boston
    Sends a seal ordered for Mr. Read; apologizes for having kept him waiting so long but has been involved in large, unprofitable silver-smith's work. Regrets the price he mentioned for the seal, the work being far more than he expected; however, will stand strictly to his bargain, and trusts to his generosity to pay the extra amount. Would be glad of an opportunity to do any engraving.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 July 21; A.L. 1p.; Rouse, G.
    Requests Dr. Franklin to forward to him and letters which he may have or which may arrive for him from Viginia in his care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 July 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Green, Jonas. Annapolis
    Concerning two packets sent him from the Barbadoes by Mr. James Bingham. Increase in his salary and also in his work. Begs Mr. Franklin to send him a parcel of paper and some other small articles by Mr. Daniel Rawlings. The Virginian's speech caused a deal of laughter; well-approved of by some in that colony; has not heard how the Baronet himself liked it. Weather very hot; has been troubled with fever. Sends their hearty respects to Mrs. Franklin and Miss Sally. Rejoiced to see that his brave countrymen are to be rewarded for thier expense in taking Cape Breton.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 July 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Dowse, Joseph. Boston
    Writes on behalf of Mrs. Steel, to acknowledge the many kind acts of friendship she bath received from Mr. Franklin, also to solicit the cause of his displeasure with her since her departure from Philadelphia. Mrs. Steel's great esteem for him. Requests him to sell her horse and chair and to let him know the sum of her indebtedness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 August 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Cheston, Daniel. Chester, Md
    Acknowledging his favor of the 23d ult.; applied to Mr.Edward Scott for the money; will do everything in his power to get it as soon as possible and send it up.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 August 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Mary. Newport
    The loss of Capt. Grubb's vessel with a great deal of his cargo. Acknowledging a book sent her some time before, called Pamely [Pamcla]. Her daughter, Sarah, has two sons; has taken the elder to keep for a time, both parents being weakly and poor. Heard Mr. Whitfield preach.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 September 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Knows of no one who has any Spanish paper to sell cheap. The Engraver he applied to about the plate, is an idle, lazy fellow, always making excuses; despairs of ever getting him to do it. His Long-Primer almost worn out; asks his advice about sending home for a new one. Received the Pocket Companion, is the Young Man's Companion almost done? His son is recovered but his wife is poorly.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Proc. Mass. Hist. Soc., 2d s., XVI, 189.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 September 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Concerning a debt of Mr. Franklin's he is to pay to Mr. De Lanccy; Sympathizes with him over his frequent losses. Mr. H. deprived of his position as Councillor, and out of the Governor's favor. Certain materials and their prices. The new type he has used in "The History of the Rebellion.' Various articles he wishes sent to him. Thanks God the sickness has greatly abated.
    Printed in Proc. Mass. Hist. Soc., 2d s., XVI, 190.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 September 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Cheston, Daniel. Chester, [Md.]
    Concerning the order drawn in favor of Mr. Edward Scott; has been unable to procure anything but promises. Suggests that Mr. Franklin should write a threatening line or two, which he will take care to deliver and enforce.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1747 September 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Colden, Cadwallader. New York
    Acknowledging favor of the 29th ult. Is particularly desirous of seeing "The Indian History"; gave Mr. Collinson certain papers on that subject with no thoughts of their being published; the publisher, Mr. Osborne, desires some work; recommended Mr. Franklin to him for trade in that line. Delivered Mr. Franklin's piece on Electricity to Mr. Darling. Asks his aid in the matter of a servant-man, who ran away from him the previous summer; either agree for his time or send him back. Desires news of Mr. Ermet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1748 September 2; D.S. 1p.; Strahan, William. London
    Power of attorney to Benjamin Franklin to collect money from James Read.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1750 February 5; A.L.S. 4p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Sends him all the electrical books and papers he can find. His curious pieces relating to electricity and thunder have been read before the [Royal] Society. Is making a collection of his articles and letters on electricity to put into the hands of the printer to communicate to the public. Account of an earthquake felt on the 8th inst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1750 March 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Death of the Prince of Wales.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1750 September 2; A.L.S. 5p.; Kalm, Peter. Albany
    Containing a detailed description of Niagara Falls, his journey there, his reception by Commandant Beaujeau and his French officers; if he finds this letter worthy of being printed in his newspaper, prays him to turn it into better English.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [ca. 1756 December]; L. 3p.; -----, -----
    An account of the courtship and marriage of Mr. Hubbard in his eighty-first year (our Speaker's 1 father).
    1 Thomas Hubbard, Speaker of the Massachusetts House, 1750-1758.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 February 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Perkins, John. Boston
    Acknowledging his bill, also the pamphlets sent the summer before. Pleased with Dr. Hamilton's generous defence of good Dr.Thompson, Begged Mr. Franklin's "Plain Truth" of Mrs. Mecom, as he had never seen it. Mr. Kinnersley well-received; through him, has seen some of Mr. Franklin's entertaining experiments. His opinion of this new found element [electricity]. Thinks Mr. Franklin's Rationale on Clouds and Rain, and also on the Aurora Borcalis, appears extremely probable. Would transmit his own observations on the 'Fulmen' if he has the leisure to look at them. Has bad a cold winter. Boston threatened with epidemic of small-pox; Some persons trying tar-water as a preventive; would gladly try anything Mr. Franklin may have heard of, but differs from his brethren in the affair of diet. Wishes him all the happiness in his son that his genius and accomplishments seem to promise.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 118, Note).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 June 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Acknowledges receipt of letters. New colonial maps being made. Sends books on electricity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 July 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Publication of a book on Franklin's electrical experiments. Purity of style of Bolingbroke's letters. Pleased with the Dissertation on the Increase of Mankind. Account of books purchased.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Perkins, John. Boston
    Inquires the number that died of inoculation in Philadelphia. Proportion of deaths much fewer than in 1730; thinks this due to the purging method designed to prevent the secondary fever. Decrease in inhabitants.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 118).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 August 12; Diss. Ms. 2p.; Collinson, Peter
    Hints on the incorporation of the Germans in Pennsylvania with the English and to check the increase of their power.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 August 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Collinson, Peter
    Has given Mr. Franklin's account of the Germans to Mr. Pelham and Lord Halifax, with his own seven suggestions on the incorporation of the Germans with the English, and Parliament will take some measures to remedy the situation. French expedition to the Ohio. Mr. [William] Smith a very ingenious man; pity that he is not more solid and less flighty. Disappointed at the bad luck that attended the transit of Mercury. Franklin's zeal to promote that observatioin is not enough to be commended. Has not yet heard any account of it from any of the colonies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 September 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Collinson, Peter
    Cannot understand the miscarriage of his letters. Is glad the new seminary of learning is so promising. All Europe is in agitation verifying electrical experiments on points. All commend the thought of the inventor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 October 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Perkins, John. Boston
    Acknowledging his favor of Sept. — containing certain observations. Delivered his papers on the weather to his brother [John] Franklin; sorry for his bad state of health. Takes exception to his article on the Water-Spout; hopes to hear from him on the subject.
    Printed, for the most part, in works (sparks, VI, 136).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 October 20; A.L. 13p.; Perkins, John. Boston
    Relative to water spouts and his reasons for believing that they descend rather than ascend. Extract from a voyage which seems to have been made by a Mohammedan in 851, relative to water spouts in the Indian ocean.
    Printed, in small part, in Works (Sparks, VI, 139).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1752 October 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Perkins, John. Boston
    Enclosing all he has to say on the matter; his motives for expressing these opinions; has not been able to differ with Mr. Franklin in any other of his supppositions, even in this is open to conviction. Announces death of Dr. W. Douglass of an apoplectic fit; left large estate and one child whom he acknowledged as his son but never adopted; no will has been found.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 138).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 January 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Disheartened at the loss of Captain Davis. The Proprietor has given him assurance that he will support a rectorship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 January 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Dress goods sent to Mrs. Franklin; electrical books to him. His laudable public spirit. Increased hopes of a discovery of the Northwest Passage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 March 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Sends books by this ship and the next. Duke of Richmond inquired very particularly about the Proprietor. Richard's son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Mitchell, James. York
    Acknowledging his facor of 28th ult. The order on him in favor of Mrs. Benger for $100 shall be punctually paid when presented. By next post will send an acct. of the stoves paid and those on hand. Asks him to forward the enclosed to his son-in-law, if he has arrived at New York.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 June 14; D.S. 2p.; Holland, Samuel. Lancaster, Pa
    Bond for B#100.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 June 14; D.S. 1p.; Holland, Samuel. Lancaster, Pa
    Agreement between Samuel Holland and Benjamin Franklin, printers, as to rent for printing press.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 July 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Acknowledges receipt of letters. Orders eight boxes of seeds from J[ohn] Bartram.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 July 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Glad to hear of the success of Mr. Peter's sermon. The Proprietor's bounty to the Academy. Account of AbbC) Nollet's attempt at Paris to declare that Franklin's electrical discoveries could not be verified, and the frustration of the attempt of a nobleman.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 July 25; D.S. 1p.; Harvard College. Cambridge
    Diploma of Master of Arts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 September 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Has recommended Mr. [William] Smith to Mr. Penn, who he hopes will endow a professorship in the Academy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 November 19; Colden, Cadwallader, 1688-1776
    In reference to water spouts.
    Printed in works (Sparks, VI, 177).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1753 November 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, John. Boston
    Furnace stands well; the glassmen fully employed in making window glass and bottles, expects the former will be thought good enough to glaze the church. Reasons for the small profits incident to the position of General Postmaster; dishonesty of post-riders. Brother Peter in town and talks of writing to Franklin. Progress of the buildings; a tenant has bespoke one of them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1753 February]; A.L.S. 1p.; Perkins, John. Boston
    Sends an inclosure relative to a new thought in natural philosophy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 January 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    The Proprietor is ardent in promoting schools for teaching the Germans and solicitous about the prosperity of the Academy. A gold medal to be presented to Mr. Franklin by the Royal Society for his electrical discoveries. The aggressions of the French. Hearty wishes that Reverend [William] Smith may have a safe return passage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 February 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Colden, Cadwallader. Coldengham
    Acknowledging his favors of Dec. 6th and Jan. 1st. The value he places on Mr. Franklin's approbation and esteem. His political opinions; his admiration for the English Constitution; thinks America in greater danger from Popular Licentiousness than from any abuse in their governors, though some of them have been bad enough. Lord Halifax's approval of his conduct. Exceedingly pleased with Franklin's observations on "The Increase of Mankind"; the last paragraph being the only one liable to exception, thinks it a pity it should end the discourse. Has been revising his own Principles in order to challenge all opposition. His son David pleased with Mr. Franklin's notice of his performance. Sends Pike's book by his son, Alexander.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 February; A.L.S. 4p.; Smith, William. London
    Sent a long letter to Mr. Penn containing the scheme for Franklin's Academy and the arguments for it. Mr. Penn has come into every part of it and will give a yearly sumy for some time, and when he comes to Pennsylvania intends to give a manor to the Academy for certain purposes. The proprietor had a design in view of his own, of which he intended to be the founder, but after argument, agreed to ingraft his scheme upon Franklin's in the two foundations proposed, provided Mr. Smith would be the person to execute them. To this he agreed, trusting that it would be welcome to the trustees. Sees a great deal of Mr. Penn, who consults him on every point that relates to literature in hiscountry. His letter laid before the Society entrusted with the moneys for the Germans, and they are satisfied that the education of youth ought to be their more immediate object. The management of this important trust should devolve upon men of the first rank of Pennyslvania and not upon clergy who depend on Dutch synods. Hopes to see all such dependence shaken off once they can supply the Germans with ministers from the Academy. Outline of the scheme which he has laid before the Society. Smelled out and broke the neck of Mr. Tennent's scheme, which was for the benefit of the Jersey College, by monopolizing the education of German clergy. His proposition of a German professor of divinity at the Academy to prevent this scheme of drawing the Pennsylvania Germans to the Jersey College. The Proprietor has agreed to give ten or twelve acres of land to every schoolmaster. Has drawn out a short memorial of the case of the Germans without any reasonings or education, which is to be distributed and collections solicited in both houses of Parliament. He doubts not the contributions will amount to a great sum, his Majestry having given B#1,000 and the Princess Dowager B#100. The Archbishop has greatly encouraged him. Col. Martin, of Antigua, if Mr. Smith returns, will send his youngest son to the Academy, and Mr. Penn talks of sending out a nephew. He (Smith) will return with a formed scheme and an appointement of trustees.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 March 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Miscarriage of letters sent by Captain Mitchell. Increased interest of the Proprietor in the Academy. The gold medal from the Royal Society is being sent by [William] Smith. Disturbances in the Assemblies of Virginia and New york. Prof.[Peter] Kalm is publishing his American travels in Swedish. Further electrical experiments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 March 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Jackson, Richard. Inner Temple
    Has ventured to commit to paper certain thoughts on the subject of a Medium of Commerce including a plan of a provincial bank; explains his views. Favourable impression, his friend. Mr. Smith, created at Cambridge, Concerning the new model of the Administration, made necessary by Mr.Pelham's death, though the Lord Chancellor, the Duke of Newcastle and most of the old friends of Sir Robert Walpole, hold together, yet they find it difficult to satisfy Mr. Fox, Secretary at War; Mr. Fox's powerful connections, said to extend even among the Royal Family; his refusing the office of Secretary of State; discovered it would curtail his powers in the House of Commons; rumor that he is to quit everything; Public Service cannot but suffer by this dissension.
    (See page 12, LII, 23.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1754?] March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Logan, James. London
    Quoting a paragraph from his brother's letter, concerning the strange attitude of their Governor in not taking certain measures to make peace with the Indians, in accordance with his instructions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 March 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Dalibard, Thomas François. Paris
    Franklin's name justly reverenced in France by all, except a small number of electricians, like l'Abb"C) Nollet, who are jealous of his discoveries.
    In French.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 193).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 June 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Timothy, Peter. Charles Town
    Acknowledging favor of Apr. 28th by Capt. Robeson which caused him great concern though its severity was probably marited; explains why he did not send the money. Sends $65 by Rudeman Robeson; thinks that will about balance his account. Can send no paper as yet. For 4 months has been the sole occupant of his printing-office, except a negro boy; discharged his villaionour apprentice, who might have been of vast service to him had he not been addicted to drink, play and scandalous company.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 June 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Daniell, William. Kingston
    Desirous of dealing with him for paper; asks for certain samples and prices.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 June 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Daniell, William. Kingston
    Since his last, has received Mr. Franklin's letter, telling him the paper has not arrived; will give more particular directions to the captain that carries them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 September 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, John. Boston
    Expected to hear complaints from Philadelphia of hot weather. Concerning Blanchard's Remedy for the Stone; thinks it might he service able in his disorder; means he has taken to procure some. Messages his wife sends. The enclosed is to be forwarded to Mr. Beacham's son, who is sick.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754 November 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Daniell, William. Kingston
    Acknowledging the receipt of 10 reams of paper, and asking for fifty more, as he is really much in want.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1754; 11p.; Jackson, Richard
    Observations upon a medium of commerce. (See I, 24.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1754?]; A.N.S. 1p.; Kemble, Peter. New York
    A request to forward an inclosure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 4p.; -----, -----
    Schemes for uniting the strength of the Colonies; puts Mr. Davenant's published in 1698, ahead of all others; emphasizes its good points. (Final part missing.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1755 June 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Timothy, Peter. Charles Town
    Acknowledging receipt of paper. Begs again for statement of his account. If his study of the Electrical Arcana, and public affairs leave him any leisure, begs for a line or two. Wretched management of Indian affairs by the Governor of South Carolina; effect on his press. Announces birth of 6th child and only son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1755 June 27; A.L.S. 4p.; Brooke, Richard. Maryland
    Thanking him for his hospitality during his visit to Philadelphia last year. A detailed account of the effects produced on Mrs. Addison's house in his neighborhood by a stroke of lightning at the end of last May. The noise awakened Mrs. Addison who observed two balls of fire in her room, about the size of a pigeon's egg, which soon went out and left for a considerable time afterward a strong sulphurous smell in the room. Asks numerous questions suggested by this incident.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1755 June 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William. Philadelphia